[Music]
for a growing number of futurists
culture analysts and seekers Jordan Hall
has become a key mode of signal in a
world of increasing noise co-founder of
newer hacker collective futurist
sorcerer angel investor tech
entrepreneur these are just some of the
hats you will find on his various BIOS
hats are interesting but they are hats
as Lamanna Jordan shows up the dialogue
in combination with the relevance of his
thought that is of key interest to many
I hope that for many who track the
ongoing development of the cluster of
memes and names associated with game B
and the Integris transformation of self
and society now this offers a unique and
interesting window into some speculative
metaphysics characteristic of the
transformation in which we participate
no answers here certainly not for me
hopefully some relevant questions in
transformation though whether you're
watching on YouTube or listening as a
podcast remember to subscribe and hit
the bell to track upcoming releases much
love Jordan hi hello how are you
good you're coming in your fuzzy my
fuzzy you were you're a bit fuzzy let's
see how it lets see how it takes care of
itself
Australia still has or at least where I
am which is very central to the heart of
Melbourne realistically speaking it
still has ADSL too so not the best not
the best connection in the world so yeah
I mean maybe we'll see how it europe
your a bit clearer now I can see well
enough yeah yeah I'm recording myself
with a separate camera and the your
audio your hearing is not from this
microphone so I'll edit that in
afterwards so the main thing is is that
you're clear and you seem to be clear
that I'm I'm actually entirely a
computer deep fake simulation so we can
just send you the file afterwards it'll
be perfect well you've got one of those
voices that I could see being
particularly susceptible to that
actually how are you anyway I mean look
this is a bit of a strange thing
to be doing in in some sense how do you
feel
logging on and meeting me and sort of I
have a lot of respect for people that do
that because there's a sense in which
it's stepping into the unknown in quite
a real sense for me it's actually always
been well I can't say always actually be
perfectly frank for the better part of
my life actually didn't spend much time
talking with other people in general and
certainly not talking with other people
telephonically but something along the
lines of improvisation mm-hmm is more
than that it's pretty natural for me I
don't tend to plan what it is that I'm
about to do in the biological sense I
mean I have plans in life I'm planning
on going out to eat for example but I'm
more of a theater performer than I am a
film performer yeah and so I'm actually
quite happy to be put into a context
where the the conversation actually
provokes possibility yeah I feel no
interest whatsoever being a message so
as a consequence it's quite nice to just
for conversation if somebody wants to
record it and share with other people I
suppose that's okay yeah I feel very
similar I feel actually quite
uncomfortable about saying many things
to people at all it's becoming more and
more that way apart from if it's in
dialogue with them yeah so yeah I think
I know what you're saying yeah I mean
there's there's lots of different
reasons for that in different things we
could go down now I've so when I load up
Skype it starts recording automatically
now we don't have to use anything that
just occurred there usually I would say
okay now everything from this point will
take as the recording so yeah look I
mean the way I'm looking at this is that
the only difference between me wanting
to talk to you and have a conversation
offline versus online it's the simple
fact that the mechanism for doing so
involves an audience so in that sense
yeah I'm I'm good to go but then there's
also I'm gonna have to do that this kind
of weird abstract thing where all of a
sudden here we go we move into that
different space so anytime from when
were like oh we could super begin where
we begin and this part right now that
we're having is that being had out out
loud in front of other people who are
watching right now sure
I'm merely happy for that but I usually
there's only want to one question I
should ask which is how long do I have
before like what are the considerations
over your time here I planned in some
sense to ask you to begin with why you
here and what are you doing this form
and you've already given a partial
answer that you need the intrigue and
dialogue and not being disposed just to
speak in that transmission based way
from speaker to audience that's not what
compels you
you're looking to engage in a some sort
of collaboration fundamentally to
express what's authentic and what comes
up so perhaps the next question is what
are your priorities in life hmm well I
think what I what I might do to be able
to respond to that is actually just
think about where do I actually spend my
time yes that'll is a nice concrete way
of assessing that so I spend quite the
majority of my time as a parent so I
would say the primary priority is to be
a good parent particularly so if you add
the amount of time that I spend in
relationship with my kids to the amount
of time that I spend either preparing to
be in relationship or dialogue in with
other people about that then that's
probably even the majority of my waking
hours
meant in that context I spend a
meaningful amount of time it's a funny
thing to say but maybe contemplating
things and it seems that the things that
I'm contemplating are things that have
they had a come up I've learned over the
past I guess forty eight years but over
the past ten years or so in particular I
don't know a certain approach to how I
allow my attention to be directed even
the fact they were on this call is an
example of that so I you may say that I
follow my gut that's kind of a nice
simple way of putting it it's not as
simple as that but there's a way and
that brings me into the contemplation
and I I do I think have a a preference
for clear and deep thinking and so nine
counts and it seems worth the tending to
you at all I often find myself
contemplating it rather deeply and so I
spend a lot of my time doing that
there's more if you can go on obviously
I have a large amount of hours of my
life but this seems like a good place to
start yeah
contemplation deep thinking following
the gut these three things together I
think lead us in an interesting
direction because the kind of thinking
that interests me the most although of
course I am interested in tight analytic
thinking and doing my best to be clear
but it's also what you're thinking about
and just what the fuck are you doing and
just how are you discerning between the
qualitative information that you receive
in your life how are you moving towards
the better and not the worse how are you
moving towards a place of self
transcendence rather than a never
closing spiral of delusion there's a
sense in which this got that perhaps
your reference here is this some more
effective
perhaps and okay here I'm gonna just
Chuck a term that's gonna introduce a
whole nother dimension to this perhaps a
somewhat more mystical capacity because
what are we following the following
feelings in the body we're following
emotional orientation I mean ultimately
where I'd quite like to get to just to
put cards out on the table which an
interest of mine and something I sense
you should sense you share as well as
this relationship this is a sort of
mystical contemplation but perhaps to
make the question a bit more succinct
bit more clear what are the kinds of
thinking that you engage in that you
find most meaningful well exactly as you
say it's a an experience that involves
allowing a particular mystery I suppose
to percolate and to
embody itself in I suppose the capacity
to be expressed so that's the one that I
find the most meaningful you have a
blend of expression I respect a lot
which is clarity plus plus that nod to
the unknown in a more poetic way how it
comes across to me if you're interested
when I read for example your medium
articles the method of conveying comes
across as quite analytical but there is
a sense in which well I mean quite
explicitly you are tenderly in
expressing out embodying out a
connection to the realization of a story
in which you're not quite sure the role
you're actually playing and I think
there's something profoundly true about
that however it's in our expressing it
and coming into relationships with each
other that we encounter what's at least
somewhat required or somewhat able to
help aid our understanding and just what
it is we're doing
but it's this time period thing is very
very challenging over how long should we
be taking in how long is how long is the
frame of reference to sort of judge just
what role we're playing in some
situation here and I find that that that
problem is um is a really devilish one
and so I actually would quite like to
ask you back to the question of
priorities what are you what would you
like to achieve in dialogue with people
online right now you've been speaking to
John Devaki you've had a number of
appearances with rebel wisdom you seem
to be from someone who's paid attention
to this a lot and from someone who's
tracking many of the same memes and
looking to embody them in the world to
some extent to bring people together to
involve them in conversation to pay
attention to the feeling along with the
words and perhaps the feeling more
importantly than the words to attempt to
experiment with collective sense making
to try and lead in some sense or provide
the toolkit do a little bit of
orchestration for something that
fundamentally is not yours to
orchestrate that's an interesting thing
so but never the so so there's ceding
something and then there's also always
hang on I'm not interested in telling
anybody a message that they're not
interested to participate in that
realization with so it becomes actually
quite difficult to speak about what it
is you're doing so I've been a so that's
why the importance is to step in and
dialogue and see what comes up could you
talk a little bit to the lay of the land
you see at a more systemic level in
society at the moment how the individual
finds himself in that and what you
believe would would be a success for you
if you can move the needle towards a
direction of a better relationship
between an individual and a sustainable
world oh that's a lot let's see
well the thing that's coming up most
clearly right now is a story that I've
felt very close to for some time and it
has to do with the notion both that
we're in a moment of real change capital
R capital E and also that this moment of
real change is a moment that is a part
of a longer arc there's some kind of
continuity to change as well they were
connected to something or are there's a
way for us to have some relationship
with the change that is not entirely
incomprehensible and so this is where
for example of the analytic work shows
up it's actually is there anything that
we can say anything that we can actually
make available to that part of our mind
into our being that can be helpful and
useful as for endeavoured to go through
this and for that matter
just communicating the people for whom
that particular style of communication
is their preference and the my sense my
deep sense my considered sense is that
the the quality the magnitude and the
quality of the change is truly profound
in a way that is very difficult I think
for people to conceive of because it is
in fact that that true
I actually remember being at a the very
first time I ever went to a place called
the Aspen Institute and there was a
gentleman there who'd been the CEO of a
pretty significant company and for some
reason I don't really know the backstory
had been working on a notation that he
gave at this conference and in the
presentation he said our our it is our
considered judgment that is our
assessment for the people who are
gathered here many of whom
actually with other important people
Capital high capital B that the the
information revolution where we want to
call that will be on the order of
magnitude of at least ten times as
impactful as the Industrial Revolution
okay so this was important people and
this was serious people articulating
this notion and intended to be taken
seriously in a venue where that sort of
thing happened but then I just stopped
for myself just sitting there in the
room just thinking well okay well with
that every what does that actually imply
let's just take a look back at what the
Industrial Revolution did across all the
different domains of human experience in
terms of religion in terms of how we
lived who we lived with how we lived our
lives when we thought of as being life
our concepts our notions our values our
aesthetics and of course the answer is
it was tremendously significant
incomprehensible in many deep senses
like the people before and after
we're as different as each other as a
people before and after the Cultural
Revolution and the proposition that you
might have an event ten times as
significant there would happen over a
frame frame 1/3 1/6 as much time what I
noticed was that was not taken seriously
at all it was not actually even
conceptualized and I was got curious
about that this is quite a while ago
maybe gosh 20 years ago now so I think a
part of it is just a natural
characteristic on my on my part to
pursue continuity in reality to try to
hold as coherent and without that
suppose there would be illusion or
without completion a relationship
with reality there's an integrity so if
it turns out that it is proposed to be
the case that an event ten times the
order of magnitude the industry
revolution revolution is happening and
is likely to unfurl before the end of
the century then okay let's just take
seriously what that means and run it
down all the way to the end and it has
seemed to be the case over the past 15
years or so as I've been engaging in
this kind of thing in earnest that
certain characteristics of my
personality which may or may not be
pleasant in all cases are of some
service in this particular effort list
of phrase I actually learned this from
the whole Jordan Peterson universe
disagreeableness I have a certain
disagreeableness the the fact that my
particular perspective may not be shared
by the people around me does not I'm not
gonna say in the least but pretty close
sway the perspective that I have
although I listen very closely so it's
not that I don't listen to other
people's perspectives it's just the fact
that other people have the perspectives
that that a group has the perspective is
not in and of itself cause me to believe
that it's true and then I guess there's
a just a strong sense that they're
wanting to for people to actually be
able to as individuals live good lives
for everyone ultimately I certainly have
the highest degree of concern for people
who are you bailed to be younger but to
just be witness to the the fact that
we're in a circumstance that we could
just without a home for my perspective
is that a whole lot of effort radically
transformed the quality of life and
illness of life of literally everyone in
a way that is not just enduring but is
in this very bizarre sense it's the only
possible way for us to actually continue
to the last as a species or at least as
a civilization I kind of can't look away
from that fact
yeah I think I understand and then I I
noticed that there's not a dine stein
quote the one that we're not going to be
able to to do the thing using the thing
that got us here right was frankly hard
one for me I struggled quite mightily to
figure out how to do the thing using the
stuff that got us here can we use
excellence and technical capacity to
figure this thing out and it wasn't
until in fact I was quite confident
through both theory and practice that
this was not possible at all that I
began in earnestly entering into what we
might call exploring truly through the
banality or being in relationship with
mystery and so in that context there is
a an awareness of as you say like a
non-centrality a I'm just listening and
endeavoring to most fully and clearly
express and participate with that which
seems to be the most true and there is
to the extent that I can nothing between
me and that which seems to be true
and obviously my capacity to do that is
as limited as anyone elses but that's
the notion and
it is what it is
what role does teleology play in your
worldview hmm this is a very interesting
question I actually found myself
contemplating it the past three days
actually I think somebody brought it to
my attention was it you no no I mean I
think I think the relationship between
teleology and relevance realization is
something that's quite on the pulse is
something I thought a lot for a while
I'm very very excited by the unfurling
involved of John's John's work which is
purely novel for me yeah at all
I've been studying I suppose to some
degree John's work for about three or
four years oh wow well lucky you yeah
it's fortunate well he had a
conversation with Jordan Peterson that's
been watched a couple hundred thousand
times I think that was in 2015 and that
was my yeah that's how I found what he
was up to and I've been studying Jordan
Peterson's work for a couple years
before then and yeah I mean what has
emerged that the right relevance
realization there was something in you
they gave you a sense that to study
Jordan Peterson was a worthy endeavor
yeah and that as you came across John it
oriented you in the direction of John to
apparently some meaningful extend
teleology I think is a needs to be held
carefully and actually teased apart in
some sense in some very simple sense
there's an obvious for shortness about
certain kinds of T V ology and chaos
theory or complexity today we would just
call these basins of attraction so if I
if I put the marble at the top of the
bowl I can tell you logically proposed
that it will end up at the bottom of the
bowl ad infinitum there's many many many
things that have
a characteristic where the future is
very easy to predict given the current
context and of course contrariwise there
are other systems where the possibility
of predicting the futures in fact zero
okay that's a nice way of grasping
reality so there's sort of a meta
question or a bigger question which is
is there something about the nature of
the reality that we're currently in that
is at the former case is it more like a
basin of Attraction is there's something
about it that we can use to make strong
predictions or even certain predictions
about the future States or is it more
like the latter case and by example the
good folks of the 19th century who
teased apart thermodynamics made some
very specific predictions about the heat
death of the universe but of course the
notion of Talos is almost invoking a
design intentionality that it's a narrow
throne and about this I I do not know I
simply do not know
so what the wheel what gets things going
what moves the wheel what gets things
going and yeah I don't know if and I
mean here perhaps you can correct me but
in my thinking about teleology why tell
us is something that is difficult to
shake offers I'm not sure how I'm not
sure how there can be an experience of
coherence without a multiplicity without
that without a multiplicity of things
being in relation with one another by
virtue of their capacity to be in
relationship ultimately with a higher
unity and the idea that the realization
of our nature whatever is given in our
capacity to experience at all that there
can be experience that can it that it
can be in a meaningful qualitative
relationship that there can be coherence
through change through transformation
that there is coherence to emerge again
after the dissolution after death all of
that somehow has to be nested if that's
not nested in some meaningful
orientation not necessarily to a
blueprint of the final thing that has to
be in some fixed sense of end state but
it's like a that the image in my mind is
a is our harmonic dance around a
continually moving center but that
nevertheless all those pieces in the
dance
gain their coherence in part not only by
relationship to each other but by
relationship to the fact that there is a
wandering that there is a center which
moves so the whole process itself is
what's real but the rear the
re-imagination of a point of coherence
that binds and draws I I don't like I
don't get I don't get how there can be
things that talk to each other that can
be in meaningful relationship with each
other if there is not in some sense a
continuity continuity some sort of unity
wholeness to put it yes homemaking so my
so my thoughts and the reason I find so
much resonance with yourself and Daniel
smacking burger and also Forrest Landry
who I was reading one of his essays on
consciousness actually just before we
began this conversation I've just
started I just found his his work
through
well first through the transition video
that you put online which I actually got
a small group of people together in a
cinema to watch actually a few months
ago and to discuss it yeah yeah yeah I
mean it's been a work in progress to get
to this point to talk to you Jordan but
um I would I would point your attention
to a work of forests called the
effective choice mm-hmm I get the
feeling that that would probably be the
one there would be the most relevant to
you
well in that video he says love is that
which enables choice and I can get in
touch with I can get in touch with that
I believe how do you respond to that
notion well that's actually a very big
question because it requires we first be
true the croc love and mutually grok
choice usually notice very grok a way of
grasping and sharing something which is
almost at the level of participating in
consciousness together sure yep with you
yep
Oh My heavens that is extraordinarily
sick that's a very large thing I can
read something out that might help you
if you like something you wrote
something I wrote something you wrote so
it's fun
yeah and I mean this is gonna get there
perhaps in a bit of a roundabout way and
I am shoehorning this in but you know
everything's connected perhaps it is not
that we need to become conscious of
power but that power needs to become
conscious of power are becoming self
conscious of power itself go back and
look at the five orders of power order
five being able to create values no
longer dependent upon pre-existing and
inherited values one can transcend the
existing power systems and begin
bestowing value creating new evaluations
new distinctions but if this is outside
of the power systems from where does
this power to create values come power
looks like a geology plate tectonics the
values and power systems that distribute
them are at the surface but that is all
that they are a thin surface resting on
a molten core occasionally this core
will erupt and a form of power will
break
the surface which is entirely new and
different occasionally ebbs and flows in
the subterranean world will determine
that huge chunks of the surface will
break apart and flow occasionally
someone will dive down deep deep into
the heart of the world and tap into this
source herein lies power with a
different name entirely culture is
powerful but it is also many voiced
moreover all culture rests as a thin
very thin skin upon the molten core of
our human inheritance forces that were
ancient when the pyramids were conceived
rise up to ensure that will fulfill a
destiny that is beyond our civilized
vanity I haven't met that guy in quite
some time wrote that on a train in 2002
[Music]
hmm Wow and now to connect that to
forests phrase
yeah it's um
humility I think is what comes to me
there the the humility of really
recognizing the degree to which that
call of let nothing come between me and
love means stripping yourself down of
all that which you and anyone else ever
has constructed being naked before
[Music]
purity but for fluorescence and
the holiness then of this notion choice
yeah
imagine this or think about this the
idea of free will the notion that were
the question of whether or whether
whether we do or do not have free will
is a to me a very profane question much
more meaningful I think is to stand
amazed at the fact that that which is we
is nothing more or less than choice
which of course then would allow us to
hold the concept of sacred somewhat
simply sacred is to enable choice to
enable choice to be furthered and then
we can do the construction mm-hmm
sacred is love love is that which
enables choice we can maybe breathe in a
relationship with the the feeling of
being connected that sense of wholeness
he referred to earlier the feeling of
being part of a continuity and also the
feeling of being each of us a moment a
very precise moment of choice we are
involved
that is meaningfulness mm-hmm
putting boundaries down and stepping off
again into the unknown and disconnection
becomes and is of course a part of
enabling choice so we in this way love
is also letting go and sovereignty
perhaps then I mean not perhaps mean is
then the capacity to reconnect and
reorient once you've departed at least
to some degree but it's this mystical
capacity to connect back up again it's
like okay
what what's that thing and and that is
that is also love and affirmation right
so that which enables choice but but
that is not always my experience of of
love precisely I mean it's I I mean
maybe I'm thinking about that in the
wrong way like love isn't just the sort
of abstract reflection of enabling
someone's choice it's certainly you know
an embodied continuity with it God here
and now yeah so this maybe we can add
the notion of discernment mmm-hmm if you
had the notion of discernment and you
think about the context of so what I
mean by discernment is a faculty or at
least a part of the story a part of the
notion of discernment is a faculty for
being able to make it's in relationship
with being able to make good choices so
discernment helps us make good choices
effective choices in forest language and
its
it's complex meaning that it's nuanced
and subtle and diverse and it's
listening to or perceiving the whole so
to see it's in fact precisely the
Faculty of that is able to perceive the
whole and to allow the whole to express
itself into choice so if you imagine as
a parent and you're in relationship with
your child and you are using discernment
in making the choices the parenting
choices to the degree to which you are
able to truly truly really listen in
deeply with that Faculty of discernment
two things will become quite clear first
is that you will constantly be finding
all of your choices are orienting in the
direction of supporting and enabling the
choice of your child those in their
capacity to make choices and second you
will then know that this is in fact love
that is what love is so you are acting
as a conduit you are a relationship with
and acting as a conduit of and
expressing so that's another way of
maybe feeling making more concrete a
little bit more embodied
yeah I hear you and I resonates strongly
with all of that just trying to think
whether to track back and clarify my
sense of love as an affirmation in
relationship to that or just to move on
there's a sense in which I mean love as
an affirmation as the like the bedrock
ember from which you're sort of
acceptance of that pre-given will to
participate becomes then a valuing of
your capacity to participate and
therefore make choices in relationship
and connection with everyone else well I
think I hear you saying I would perhaps
use John's well probably not John's but
in my lexicon I'm identifying with John
notion of participatory no it sure
absolutely
so when you say affirmation you mean a
participatory affirmation yes or to be
connected absolutely absolutely you know
the connection the connection I mean and
I don't know where to take this is going
to be particularly a bit out there but
the connection then between the
participatory knowing and the systemic
or abstract formulations that become
guidelines fixed structures security
structures of behavior this then becomes
very central to the challenge and maybe
can move us in the direction of what you
take the requirements of an emerging
meta psycho technology to be yeah you
are definitely
this is deep water this is intense
he gave me an hour I don't think I could
survive two hours okay okay so let me
make your very practical look I was
having a conversation today with a group
of collaborators and we're really deeply
looking at exactly this question
obviously it's pretty much all I do and
we were talking about the kind of
culture that would be able to support
[Music]
coherence and of course this requires us
to be very aware of precisely the
challenge in question of the finger
being taken for the moon for the culture
being taken for the thing as opposed to
the culture supporting the thing who
this is an extraordinarily non-trivial
problem oh yeah
for example just very concretely we were
conceptualizing two gatherings of people
and already are beginning the process of
actually intentionally deconstructing
and reacts pressing the same cultural
artifacts in a different mode so as to
insulate the tendency to fetishize this
isn't a cure this is just an Amelia
palliative 2 for that tendency one of
the the nice things that feels like it's
a helpful in where we're headed
it is acceleration you know in the early
days let's say 3000 BC or so you could
go a couple thousand years with some
fetishized
two artifacts they were very much not
the thing but the pace of change was so
slow that for several thousand years
they could be taken as the thing in that
that would be okay now part of the
reason why we are able to be where we
are right now is that the pace of change
is accelerated so quickly that by the
time of thing but the time of cultural
artifact is is fetishized things have
moved on and it's that that metaphor of
the thin crust on top of the molten lava
the temperature is increasing and so
once you have actually achieved a
velocity of change that is adequate to
cause the ability of the lava to never
be able to become solid and it's a
culture that is premise taun itself
being renewing let me see if I can do
this right it's almost there there's a
location in culture space that has a
relationship with the way that culture
enables intelligence to modify culture
such that the pace of change is high
enough that it is impossible for
intelligence to fetishize culture
because if it does fetishize culture it
evaporates into obsolescence or
extinction in such a rapid timeframe
that it is a a non-viable pap does that
make any sense yeah perhaps it could be
something like we all are in fact
participating in an improvisational
sketch and well you've got to improvise
and not just repeat what was improvised
moments before once you've actually
dropped into an improvisational mode and
that's a very good way of putting it so
we are in the process of shifting from a
scripted mode to an improvisational mode
yeah
and there's something about once you've
shifted stabili into an improvisational
mode you discover that the kind of mind
that responds to improvisational mode is
also a kind of mind that can keep the
improvisational mode Integris rather
than devolving back into a scripted mode
that's the key it's to recognizing the
tortured mind our co-creative and
there's a move where there's a mind
that's able to move us into a
improvisational culture which then
supports the kind of mind that would be
an improvisational mind that then
stabili maintains the flow because there
is something about the improvisational
space that is in fact actually stable
metastable yeah yeah and then we'll find
out that weirds funny like the the the
the stanza from Shakespeare all the
world's a stage and all the men and
women merely players they have their
exits and their entrances and in his
time each man will play many parts or
something like this it's like I don't
know what sort of that the dance is like
a meta realization of performance and we
are performing all along and this is
also brings us back into teleology
mmm-hmm
because it is in fact quite likely that
if this metastable state is then the
arrow throw in that direction is at
least as old as biological evolution
yeah and and then like okay there we're
gonna start talking about the
relationship between the biology and the
metaphysics cuz it's like you know
because you know young would say you
know the archetypes at least as old as
you know the biological lineage or
something like this we can say at least
they're as far back as what has been
encoded into the adaptive patterns of
you know dissolution and reintegration
and transformation over time associated
with them with that but then you know of
course like then it's like well what
sort of process what sort of
metaphysical process enables like how do
we make sense of and then for me this
the line between psychology and
metaphysics becomes blurred and then you
end up with images of mandalas and you
know like a many face to God and what
are you gonna do just draw a circle in
the ground
I think probably so but so but and I
know and I really don't and I'm knees on
the ground mouth open hands back for all
of that but um I was gonna say that's
probably better that's much closer to
what you're gonna do yeah yeah well I
mean as to some extent can speak from
experience in terms of at least the the
sense of wonder and terror you know so
okay so I my sense of the group
interactions that may be helpful to
model so that effective generative
loving communication and transformation
is present and speaks to the manifold
dimensions of the collective psyche as
expressed to different degrees and the
individuals who might be watching or
participating would be something like a
good story
something like a good play where you
have in fact many characters yes so and
it seems like this is happening
naturally and to the extent that some
characters are left out of the play some
people get mad our stories need to get
better yeah oh yes yes and you can even
say it seems to me at least that it's
probably going to look like a story that
looks like a story that tells the story
of a story that begins to look very
different my friend Jeff Gomez has
talked about it as the transition for
the hero's journey to the collective
journey mm-hmm so imagine a story like
this be very concrete imagine a Netflix
original series cool so it's a story
it's got a script it's got characters it
has a relatively small number of
characters it's certainly not 8 billion
but the story tells the story of how a
group of people figure out how to
empower themselves to empower other
people to participate in collaborating
and in the act of watching and
perceiving this story a group of people
are inspired to imagine that perhaps
something like this might happen only to
discover that a group of people who are
in fact figuring out how to empower
themselves and how to empower other
people some of whom choose to join and
to begin participating in telling their
own story and of course because this
entire story is the story of thug they
are furthering choice they are enabling
still more people to become aware of and
to choose to participate in the
expanding wave front of this new
collaborative culture we've been talking
about that seems right to me something
like that certainly would make for a
good story
down the line if we speculate that there
are multiple communities in a somewhat
decentralized way participating in the
co-creation of stories for them to in
fact be enabling choice they must remain
in appropriate connection with all the
other nodes doing the same where and
there's something
there's something very interests so
there's a again there's another store as
a meta story like what like the
mechanism something that scares me and
this is more of a mystical thought sort
of is the development of particular like
could some of those little nodes cluster
towards the propagation or the support
of one particular face of the god of one
particular God like there would be a god
of a Greek play or something that was
more associated with that particular
play than another and then and like like
how frak like it the fracturing like how
its it's again like how how the
different cogs can be can come in
together at a different level and be
coherent with one another in
participation appropriately around the
whole connecting there's the mechanism
of choosing of realizing what should
speak for the group still remains
important to the extent that we have
coherence between all these different
communities so it's you know like this
and then like this and it's still a it's
still a whole like it's a whole are key
what we're speaking about so the MIT but
the mechanism of movement with it like
within levels and then moving up is
still that has to be there and saw
standard that's um I have nothing I have
nothing to sensible to say about any of
this so she might be able to tell ha
I would like to watching the the process
in real-time that I felt like you were
actually doing some of the good stuff
what was sort of stirring within me as
you were as you were expressing yourself
was well it's definitely not gonna be
paradigmatic mind yeah
alright it's definitely not going to be
egoic
mm-hmm so that helps well yeah it you
know God funny the word God have you
encountered people in your life that the
description of a Christ inflation became
one of the more salient things to use to
describe such an individual Christ's
inflation so Jung speaks about an
inflation of the Christ archetype this
fundamental unifying archetype in some
sense of the self experienced as a sort
of imagistic Li as Christ
it's that God complex
so if we're talking about the
participation in certain things from not
being from a purely ago expand have say
that's for the right way to think about
it not purely ago ik because to the
extent that structures I mean ego is
required for there to be structure
maintained did the yeah there's it I mmm
aligning with perhaps you could talk
about paradigmatic mind and then what
the alternative is that might be a way
to concretize some things ah okay well
since you mentioned forests I would just
point you to the distinction between the
omniscient and the transcendent really I
think just for you if anybody else out
there who happens to be perceiving this
goes in that direction as well
huzzah but it's that is not a simple
path so paradigm is
model right so the construction of a
semantic framework that has a is an
extrapolation actually of an axiomatic
that identifies the truth value and the
good value of any given utterance is a
paradigm and paradigmatic mind is a a
use of the human mind that is trained in
the good use the effective use of a
given paradigm so it it understands the
axiomatic s-- or at least it's able to
generate utterances that are good and
true in the context of the axiomatic
it may not in fact understand the
axiomatic Sat all of this just has been
trained to be able to to know what is a
good move in the in the axiomatic game
and so it's schematically can be very
effective paradigmatic mind it has the
ability to stand on the shoulders of
giants without necessarily either a on
or the Giants would be doing anything
creative on its own but therefore can be
very very um well again effective if
I've a good fit to me a very nice clean
example of paradigmatic mind it might be
something like pushing the like button
on a Facebook post if you notice that
that like button is a piece of code I
don't have the slightest idea what's
happening underneath nor do I have the
slightest idea of the history of what
gave rise to the capacity of say for
example creating the JavaScript that
enables that button to be actual
real-time as opposed to static HTML
loading period out periodically you know
etc etc there's like you know an
enormous pile of stuff that has been
built inside the peregrym attic
structure
that enables this particular act on my
part that I can actually understand
within a relatively narrow band of
understanding capacity and execute on to
deliver desired results they cascade out
into a larger system so it's a very
machine ik kind of thing pair reminders
and it's extremely dependent upon the
machinery of a given society so it's
important to recognize the paradigmatic
mind is fundamentally connected to
associates to a social fabric that is
simultaneously building and constructing
the systemic dynamics the paradigmatic
mind is operating on and is enculturated
the characteristics that enable Parrott
of Megamind to be functional so it's a
whole complex it's not a single thing I
talked about the blue church for example
topologically the blue church is an
instantiation of paradigmatic mind there
are other possibilities of course but
it's a particular instantiation and then
if we want to so so why why might not it
be possible a paradigmatic mind to be
the thing that does what we were talking
about I get that you get that okay I get
that
why mmm God where I attended and we see
running out of running out of time just
radical is creation the most the the
very notion of radical which implies
implicitly the notion of change the
notion of not being connected causally
to the past creation is completely
radical it is Abney Allah creation in
its essence is absolutely unpredictable
and has no causal connection to the past
at all is it conceivable that an
instance of radical creation loses all
capacity to participate with that which
came before it
yes I would say
conceivable I would say in some sense
it's all around us I would say even the
the most fundamental characteristic of
the world that we live in is the
epiphenomena or the the buzzing blooming
confusion of these subtle radical
moments of creation
that don't quite land and don't quite
percolate into a deeper embodiment in
reality that are not graspable by the
analytic mind but also not able to be in
relationship with the impetus for
creative generation itself that we are
in relationship to yes something like
that
that is very radical that's that is very
radical yeah if I just sort of noticed I
notice it sort of everywhere there's a
pluripotency that has just beyond the
horizon and it is feels a bit like like
reaching out but not quite connecting
how is there a conflict between that
accepted realization and maintaining a
commitment to the unique value of all
human beings
I'm not sure I follow so seems to me
that the system of communication of
participatory community we're speaking
about is one which values both the
sovereignty of the individual their
unique piece their unique signal but
simultaneously their connection their
interconnection if we are to endorse a
ontology of a certain radical creativity
radical novelty that emits the or makes
possible the kind of leap in evolution
that will by necessity some experience
before others some are in relationship
with when others aren't yeah what I'm
interested in and what it seems to me to
be the case or what I'm I find it deeply
concerning that for one universe of care
to exist in isolation from another it's
this if some can be here and there is
this novel gap that we lose touch with I
I don't know how I don't know how to
pose it something in my mind anyway is
triggered there like there's certainly a
there are some pieces I have some
commitments that I care about that are
there are challenged by an attempt to
incorporate a notion of a certain sort
of radical creativity that is not
relatable to
in our capacity to bear up at the very
least to transformation and to realize a
relationship with it it comes back to
this point about how there can be
coherence between things like is there
like is it is it like a breakdown in the
fundamental interconnection between
things yeah well I think me add some
more let me just throw some more words
at the problem and see if more
connection happens what I would do is I
would make it and make a distinction
between potential and actual okay so
this because this is truly radical
creativity cannot be realized it cannot
be shared
it cannot be connected with then it
remains in the potential and why does
not render into the actual right yes I
know anyone that then at one of three
things can happen one is that's just the
way it is it just kind of stays that way
yeah another thing might be that there
is a kind of an accretion up where
something about the real has changed
such that the connection can be made and
this radical creativity is ever so
slightly less radical and therefore can
be brought into relation with what is
and therefore to be realized and made
into actual or the opposite is that some
shift may happen in the nature of the
no no actually just those two things the
third is just a second
and so in some sense you may even just
call it a path not yet is maybe a way of
thinking of it rather than not if it
happens for run for one does it happen
for all no you know in fact quite the
opposite
every singularity which of course you
are a singularity and I'm a singularity
is completely unique in this fundamental
relationship with creativity you might
even say that a large part of the work
is in our transforming that and adding
to that a capacity for that to become
more real by being more shared so is
what's happening right now is exactly
this process you're perceiving through
your singularity a field of potential
that is entirely singular to you I'm
perceiving a field of potential it's
entirely senior to me to the degree to
which I'm able in myself to be able to
bring that into a reality in just myself
and then can find a way to express it in
a fashion which can meander it shareable
so that you're then able to perceive
that in yourself we've actually now
bridged the gap and made it more real
yes so yeah yes I hear you I still have
a few things knocking away at me it's
like well if we're to dance together
then like this if that's appropriate as
a metaphor then there is a stage or a
setting or arena in which we are doing
that which itself is involved in the
transmission yes therefore that seems to
like the conflict a little bit with this
sort of a notion of complete isolation
well I didn't say complete isolation
okay I said singularity okay so in in
relationship between self yourself and
pure creativity there is absolutely
uniqueness mm-hmm we might call that
symmetry meaning not continuity in
relationship between yourself and myself
there is continuity so there is
connection that is as fundamental as
there is separation both connection and
separation are fundamental and then
there's relationship which is even more
fundamental and that's forests deepest
point actually is exactly that that the
relationship is more fundamental and
that's the process of the real the real
is the bringing the separate into
relationship with the continuous it's a
tricky business actually this is this
we're getting into some area so tarik
metaphysics that to be perfectly frank
would be better better than with forests
with me well maybe I'll have that
opportunity in the future that sounds
like it would be very fun it would be
very fun it would be an interesting
conversation people and why I would
watch yeah right well I feel like in
those last few moments there what you
said you know there was bringing a few
other pieces together that I think that
I can work with somehow there's a bit of
a more of a fitted miss like I feel a
bit more of a fitted 'no stare I'm gonna
leave some of the other questions then I
have for another time and say thank you
very much and
wish you and your family and all your
endeavors the best what's love about
whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases myself